Larry Eigner Papers 1974.0001
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
Larry Eigner Papers
1927-2003
Archives & Special Collections at the Thomas J. Dodd Research Center, University of Connecticut Library
1974.0001
4.9 Linear Feet
Born in 1927 in Swampscott, Massachusetts, Larry Eigner is an American poet affiliated with Charles Olson and the Black Mountain College.
Biography
Laurence (Larry) Eigner was a prominent American writer who authored more than 75 books and broadsides over the span of 58 years. He was born with cerebral palsy on August 7, 1927 to parents Israel and Bessie. Eigner lived most of his life—that is, his first 50 years—in his parents' Swampscott, Massachusetts home. Though he was wheelchair-bound from birth, this did not hinder him from becoming a prolific writer. Indeed, he is known for having shared and lived a social "life in letters" through his regular correspondence with friends, his publishers, other contemporary writers, and his fans.
Eigner's career was greatly encouraged by the 1940 Royal manual typewriter he received for his 13th birthday. He would often sit on the glass-enclosed front porch of his home, typewriter at the ready, using his thumb and right index finger to record his observations, experiences, and thoughts about the outside world. This porch was his makeshift office, where he committed himself to writing something—an essay, a review, a letter, or a poem—on a daily basis. His mother played a prominent role in his life, as she insisted that he receive a proper education by first tutoring him at home. Eigner was later homeschooled by his Swampscott High School teachers and also completed seven correspondence courses through the University of Chicago.
Though he did not attend North Carolina's Black Mountain College himself, Eigner is known for his affiliation with the Black Mountain poets. Esteemed alumnus Robert Creeley published Eigner's first book, From the Sustaining Air in 1953. Throughout the years his work also appeared in the Black Mountain Review as well as other publications including Poetry, The Paris Review, Chicago Review, Charles Bernstein and Bruce Andrews' L=A=N=G=U=A=G=E, and Origin.
Eigner's work relies on images, usually established with a minimal number of words, much like the style of William Carlos Williams. Though his poems are often abuzz with enthusiasm about everyday activities, they are also laden with a bittersweet pining about life's transitory nature. In contrast to his earlier work, Eigner's later pieces are shorter and attest to the progression and increasing mastery of his poetic style.
ON MY EYES (Jargon Press, 1960) was Eigner's first major collection of poems. His books following another time in fragments (Fulcrum Press, 1967) were mostly published by John Martin's Black Sparrow Press and James Weil's The Elizabeth Press. His non-poetic publications include the short story / prose collections Clouding (1968), Farther North (1969), and Country/Harbor/Quiet/Act/Around (1978). Eigner's work has also been included in anthologies such as The New American Poetry: 1945-1960 (1960), America: A Prophecy (1973), and A Gist of Origins (1975) among others.
He was one of the winners of the San Francisco State Poetry Center Award in 1983 for his book, WATERS / PLACES / A TIME (1981). His writing career was also celebrated with readings by fellow poets and friends at the University of California Art Museum in 1993.
Eigner moved to Berkeley, California, in the summer of 1978, after the death of his father. He became a noticeable figure in the area's poetry scene by providing numerous readings and hosting many visitors in his home. Eigner remained in Berkeley until his own death (due to pneumonia-related complications) on February 3, 1996. In 2010, Stanford University Press published The Collected Poems of Larry Eigner, a four-volume set that includes the more than 3,070 poems written throughout his life.
Scope and Content
Incoming and outgoing correspondence of Larry Eigner and acquaintances including David and Maria Gitin, George Bowering, Cid Corman, Robert Creeley, Robert Duncan, Vincent Ferrini, Denise Levertov and Gael Turnbull. Also includes poetry, literary magazines and an audio cassette. Additions received periodically. Related collections include George Butterick Papers, William K. Costley Papers, Vincent Ferrini Papers, James Koller Papers, Charles Olson Research Collection, James Weil Papers.
Arrangement
Two collections have been integrated into one and condensed into two boxes. Box one includes outgoing correspondence sent by Larry Eigner primarily to David and Maria Gitin including 67 letters (1970-1979) which address, but not exclusively, Eigner's poetry, poems from #76 to 1068 (1967-1978; series is incomplete; numbered poems included in letters were condensed with other numbered poems for organization), assorted papers and poems from correspondence without date or number, one notebook, mimeographed TS of a play entitled "The Reception" with occasional notes by Eigner, several literary magazines, 3 poems by David Gitin annotated by Eigner. Box two includes letters received by Larry Eigner from numerous correspondents, principally (more than 10 letters each) George Bowering, Cid Corman, Robert Creeley, Robert Duncan, Vincent Ferrini, Denise Levertov, and Gael Turnbull. Box two also includes an audiocassette of Larry Eigner reading a selection of his poems (1974).
Acquisition Information
Series I was purchased in October 1991. Series II was a gift/purchase from Eigner in 1974/1975. Later addition received from Richard Eigner.
Access
The collection is open and available for research.
Correspondence; Notebooks; Manuscripts (document genre); Personal papers; Poets; Publications (documents); Eigner, Larry, 1927-.; Ferrini, Vincent, 1913-2007; Gitin, Maria.; Gitin, David.; Turnbull, Gael; Levertov, Denise, 1923-1997; Duncan, Robert Edward; Creeley, Robert, 1926-2005; Bowering, George.
- Series I: Outgoing Correspondence, undated, 1967-1978
  - Rowan, Stephanie and Louis, 1973 October 22 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Gitin, David and Maria (11 folders)
    - Letters (35), 1970-1972 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Letters (32), 1973-1979 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Poems #76-699, 1967-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Poems #700-899b, 1972-1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Poems #900-1068 1, 1974-1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Poems and Papers, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Notebook (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - "Earth Ship" #8, 1972 February (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - TS of "The Reception" (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Magazines (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - 3 D.Gitin Poems (annotated by Eigner) (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Series II: Incoming Correspondence, undated, 1950-1977
  - Blackburn, Paul (6), 1953-1959 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Blazek, Douglas (2), 1965 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Bly, Robert (1), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Bowering, George (13), 1962-1964 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Caplan, Ronald (1), 1964 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Clark, Thomas (7), 1964-1965 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Coolidge, Clark (1), 1973 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Corman, Cid (56), 1950-1961 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Corman, Cid (74), 1962-1969 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Creeley, Bobbie (1), 1968 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Creeley, Robert (35), 1950-1968 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - Duerden, Richard (1), 1958 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Duncan, Robert (13), 1957-1970 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Jones, LeRoi (3), 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Ferrini, Vincent (11), 1954-1977 (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Fowler, Gene (1), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - Grady, Robert F. (1), 1962 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Kelly, Robert (1), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 30)
  - Laughlin, James (1), 1963 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  - Levertov, Denise (10), 1954-1971 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Mead, Matthew (2), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Millward, Pamela (1), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Minelli, Frank (1), undated (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Shayer, Michael (1), 1960 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Smith, Alexander D., Jr. (2), 1974, 1975 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Snyder, Gary (2), 1959-1960 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Souster, Raymond (2), 1954-1961 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Stefanile, Felix (1), 1955 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Taggart, John (2), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Turnbull, Gael (15), 1954-1966 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Weil, James L. (1), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Welch, Lew (1), 1961 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Whalen, Philip (2), 1958-1959 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Wieners, John (4), 1957-1958 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Williams, Jonathan (7), 1960-1967 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Williams, Terrence (2), 1966 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Wilson, Keith (3), 1965-1967 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Zukofsky, Louis (4), 1960-1968 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Unknown (1) (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - "Alan" (1) (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Audio cassette--Larry Eigner, 1974 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- Series III: Accession 2015.0091, 1927-2003; 1964-1994
  Scope and Contents
  Addition to the Larry Eigner Papers containing presentation copies of publications by poet Larry Eigner to his brother Richard and his wife Beverly (approximately 60 items), periodicals containing Eigner's poetry with handwritten marks and notations, family photographs of Larry Eigner (color and b/w), letters to Richard Eigner (1996-1998), 3 audio cassettes, 1 video cassette "Larry and Jack radio show KPFA".
  - Publications, 1956-1988 (Box 2015.0091_1)
    Box Inventory: The Beloit Poetry Journal (Spring 1956) Eigner, Larry, On My Eyes, Highlands, 1960 Satis: 3 (1961) Poetry: 100.6 (1962) Mica: 7 (1962) Satis: 5 (1962) Poetry: 103.4 (1964) Einger, Larry, duende: 6, 1964 El Corno Emplumado: 13 (1965) Camels Coming: 1 (1965) Poetry: 105.5 (1965) From a Window (October, 1965) New Measure: 4 (Winter 1966) Symptom (April 1966) Eigner, Larry, From the Sustaining Air, Toad Press, 1967 Eigner, Larry, Six Poems, Wine Press, 1967 Eigner, Larry, The- / TOWARDS AUTUMN, Black Sparrow Press, 1967 New Measure: 6 (Summer 1967) Poetry: 110.1 (1967) The Desert Review (Fall 1967) Camels Coming: 7 (1967) Eigner, Larry, air the trees, illus. Bobbie Creeley, Black Sparrow Press, 1968 Poetry: 111.6 (1968) Eigner, Larry, Valleys / Branches, Big Venus, 1969 Eigner, Larry, What You Hear, Edible Magazine, 1972 Eigner, Larry, words touching ground under, Pyramid Pamphlet: 3 (1972) Eigner, Larry, words touching ground under, Pyramid Pamphlet: 3 (1972) [damaged cover] Chelsea: 30/31 (1972) Earth Ship: 8 (1972) Eigner, Larry, looks like nothing the shadow through the air, 1972 Eigner, Larry, shape, shadow, elements, move, Sparrow: 13 (1973) Eigner, Larry, Things Strings Together of Far Away, Black Sparrow Press, 1974 Eigner, Larry, Anything on Its Side, 1974 Eigner, Larry, suddenly it gets light and dark in the street, Green Horse Booklet: 8, 1975 Big Deal: 3, ed. Barbara Baracks, (Spring 1975) Shell: 1.1, ed. Jack Kimball, (Fall/Winter 1976) Eigner, Larry, The World and Its Streets, Places, Black Swallow Press, 1977 Sun and Moon: 4 (1977) Eigner, Larry, watching how or why, The Elizabeth Press, 1977 Renegade: 1 (1978) Roof: VIII, The Segue Foundation, (1978) Eigner, Larry, Flagpole Riding, Stingy Artist: 2 (September 1978) Eigner, Larry, lined up bulk senses, Burning Deck, 1979 Eigner, Larry, time details of a tree, The Elizabeth Press, 1979 [yellow hardcover, accompanying sleeve] Eigner, Larry, time details of a tree, The Elizabeth Press, 1979 [grey paperback cover] Revue de L'Universite de Bruxelles: 1-2 (1979) Imprint: 4 (1980) Eigner, Larry, earth birds, Circle Press, 1981 Kaleidoscope: 5 (1982) Acts: 2, 1983 Eigner, Larry, there now here, James L. Weil, 1985 Eigner, Larry, some token or, James L. Weil, 1985 [grey Cover] Eigner, Larry, some token or, James L. Weil, 1985 [white Cover] Eigner, Larry, Larry Eiger Letters, eds. Robert Koick and Joseph Simas, Moving Letters Press, 1987 Brief: 1 (July 1988)
  - Publications, Correspondence, Photographs, Audio recordings, Video recordings, 1987-2003 (Box 2015.0091_2)
  - Photographs, Publications, 1968-1996 (Folder 2015.0091_3, Folder 2015.0091_4, Folder 2015.0091_5)
    Box Inventory: Symposium of the Imagination: Robert Duncan in World and Image Poem Nov: 1968 By Larry Eigner With Image By Derrick Greaves Line That May Be Cut Poetry USA Portrait of Larry Rignre as a child (black and white photograph) School group portrait featuring Larry Eigner